[Music]
We're going to present
Economic Heresy in the current context.
We can say we're going to have two
theories. I want us to separate two
theories and we're going to put the one
that everyone generally knows aside,
and for some reason, we're going to
forget about that theory, because what
I'm going to present to you is a new context
for how we study economic
theory again. Current events
are indicating that we are
very defenseless. Crises catch us and
turn us around and spin us, and
apparently we know a lot, but we
know nothing because we're being hit.
So I want to tell you
that if you come, you have the
fortune to come listen to this
conference before that great
cataclysm occurs that seems to be coming,
perhaps you can understand a
bit and help prevent such a
situation. If the
situation occurs and you know this
conference afterwards, at least you'll understand
why those events happened, what
occurred. And but let's hope we
can do it beforehand. So
Economic Heresy is going to be the new
context I'm going to present. Economic
Heresy will fundamentally rethink
the theory. We're going to rebuild it,
we're going to make it scientific, because the
problem with economic theory is
that it doesn't have a scientific
context. My name is Mauricio
Rivadeneira Mora. For you, I'm a physicist
and
economist. And we're going to
say then that Economic Heresy is
based on the book. Coming soon
"Protocols Toward a New Economic
System." "Protocols Toward a New
Economic System" develops a new
scientific and systemic method for
economic theory. Before
knowing this book, you can
find writings about it on the
webpage
http.che.com
[Music]
Economic heresy.
The
email you can use to contact
me directly is maurivadeneira
@yahoo.es or economicheresy
[Music]
@yahoo.es. Economics lacks a scientific
method. Still far from the truth, it must
be questioned without fear, because if
today's society is lost, it's not by
design of the gods, but by the
hand of man himself, by the fragility
of his thinking, by the rigidity of his
beliefs. That's why I invite you to
set aside, let's forget at this
moment what you know and
let's begin a new way of thinking about
theory. Could we build a utopia?
We can currently think
of a utopia, a new world with a
new theory. Could we believe in an
ideal country where there's no inflation, where
no country has debts, where everyone
can work, there are no poor people,
we're all rich, money is
unlimited, capitalism exists, and everyone
has social security?
I tell you that in our paradigms and
in the knowledge we have today in
current economic theory, no one would
dare say this is
possible. Our paradigms tell us
this is
impossible.
Economic Heresy wants to tell you
some reasons that justify
questioning the theory we know
today. First and fundamental: that half
of the world's population is in
poverty. Second: we approach
reality through theories and models.
In economics, we make models that we then
impose on reality. We don't look for the
best model that interprets
reality. In synthesis, we don't seek
reality. Something is
failing. Three: the method we use
is closer to mathematics than
to physics. Mathematics
allows us to create models independent of
reality. Physics, on the other hand,
forces us to find the constraints that
reality imposes on us, and both are
logical. Four: inflation, we must
know why it occurs. In general,
when a phenomenon is known, when
we know the law that produces that
phenomenon, we can control it. However,
inflation continues
to occur.
Fifth: continuing with the reasons that
justify questioning the theory we have
today in economics, we have
paradigms or fully
established beliefs. Example: that if the government
issues money, inflation occurs. I
want to tell you that I personally have
heard many explanations, but
I've never seen at least one study
where this statement can be confirmed.
No studies exist. They haven't been done.
Sixth: someone issues money, because
someone is giving money to the system.
Then it means someone is
issuing it, and what we say is
that if the government does it, it produces
inflation, but if private
parties do it, no. There's no
consistency.
Seventh: the Central Bank in all
countries of the world today has the duty to
control inflation. Now, if it succeeds,
fine, but if not, then the fault is the
government's, which is spending too much.
Notice that this isn't
consistent. Eighth: we open ourselves to an
accepted globalization. We have no way
to measure its results or to
simulate or predict its feasibility. We
don't even know if it's possible, but we
accept it without
hesitation.
Ninth: our economic theory
begins with a fundamental
postulate: resources are limited.
Hence the results: half the
population in poverty, all countries
fighting for resources with other
countries,
war. And all these are
elements that originate from the belief
that resources are limited. And there
our theory begins. That's the
fundamental principle of the theory we
have today. We're going to radically change
that principle.
Tenth: however, reality seems
to be different. Resources are unlimited. Indeed,
the sun gives us practically
unlimited energy. The sea and its
waves provide us indefinite energy.
Nanotechnology gives us a dimension
of infinite possibilities, etcetera.
Money, I want to tell you, can also be
made in any amount you want or
require, without
restrictions.
Well, I want to talk to you then now
about the context of economic theory. How
should we conceive it
today? A theory is composed of
laws and principles. In economics, the
practical part, the one that would lead us to say
what we should do, leads us, conducts us
to economic
policies. And those economic policies,
once we apply them, where do we
apply them? In institutions, where we
set goals and objectives, so
that the total context of
theory cannot be solely economic
policies, it cannot be only
institutional. We cannot say that
econometrics is not an
integration between laws, our
principles, our knowledge of
law developed through
economic policies that we apply. Then,
here we measure the results. Economic
theory must be able to
be measured. If we don't measure, if we don't verify
results experimentally, we're
not talking about a scientific
theory. So we have to
be able to interrelate both
[Music]
aspects: our experimental test and
feedback, and between one and the other
block. We cannot say that
economic theory we have, that changing
all institutions, makes no sense.
Institutions evolve with
man, with eras,
over time. So
economics isn't institutions, it's not
just economic policies. Economic
policies must be able to be
contrasted in
practice. And if what we expect equals
the result, then we can say we're
doing well.
But if we say we're going to
implement globalization according to
our principles, and then we apply
policies, neoliberal
policies, and the result is everything
collapses, well, it's not congruent,
because we did that to
be able to evolve and to move
forward, and everything is collapsing.
It means something is failing. But
what? How can we know what's
failing? So that problem,
we must be able to solve with the theory
we're building. So,
let's develop each of these
points. Let's look first at laws and
principles. Knowledge of law is
generated in the discourse of economic
theory.
This discourse, in a way, I'll put
nine equations here, not all of which we'll
accept. Nine equations that
somehow have already been
given in economics, but here we compile them. You
won't find them integrated anywhere,
but I'll show you basically
the equations we
have. I won't develop this
in detail right now. This is
just a conference to give you an
introduction. You can read it later in
the book. Economists know
this as income, the income Y,
people consume it or save it, but
when we speak in these terms,
I want you to understand it's in a country.
This is macro dimension. This isn't at an
individual level. People
consume, and this should have been called
balance, and let's leave balance there for
now. There's a second
equation of ingenuity. Product of
Keynes's ingenuity, he deciphered these
equations for economics, in which
production, which he also called Y, equal
to income, production occurs
in production of consumer goods or in
production of investment
goods. He called it Y also because
they turn out to be equal. What people
produce generates income for
people, and so they're identified. They're
equal. Since people's consumption is
equal to consumer goods, savings,
which is, or the balance people have, is
what's dedicated to investment. Investment
in what? When you make a company,
you invest in capital
goods and working
capital. Really, only those two
are where investment stays. So
what we say, that savings equals
investment, means that
investment is all in inventory,
generally in accounts or machinery,
new equipment emerging into the
economy. Keynes realized that the
system, that this part was a real part.
This is measurable. This is how a country's
gross domestic product is measured.
Keynes realized that for this, money
existed. He spoke of supply and
demand for money. We speak,
let's say, only of money, and
money was expressed as M1 and M2, and in
some contexts they put up to M4 and
even more. Really, the fundamental one is
the money supply, and this is the most
important:
M1, the money you have so these
products circulate and generate people's
income. So notice, as
if it were, as if we were talking about a
theory at the scientific level, at the
physical level, let's talk about a unified
theory. Economics must be looked at in
its context. What this invites us to,
when we put it this way, is that
we're talking about a unified
theory, a system. It's very
important to understand this is a
system.
So
money, when we make the
ratio Y over M, we then invent
the the interrelation that exists
in those two blocks: income and
production, which combines with money
so products circulate, and
we then have the definition of
velocity of money circulation. That
velocity of money circulation, and
this can already be expressed as an
equation. Even though economic
theory from there, the one everyone knows,
says this isn't an equation, but
an identity, in our context we're
going to effectively work with it as an
equation. We can express it, then,
move M to multiply on the other side, and
say Y equals V times M. That is, the
gross domestic product, or
production, is related to the
velocity of money circulation and
to the money supply of the
system. So notice, our
immediate first conclusion: if we want
gross domestic product to increase,
we have to increase the money
supply. This is going to tell us, notice,
we're going to start clashing with the
concepts from the previous theory.
That if we make emissions, let's not talk
yet about whether inflation will be
generated, but that emissions are needed
for gross domestic product to
increase. From this expression,
replacing Y with prices times
quantities, P times Q, is the quantity of
volume sold in an economy at
a given moment, it's an indicator of
production. Prices times quantities,
so we have that prices times
quantities equals V times M. From this
equation, which was called the quantitative
equation of money, it was
concluded that if M increased,
prices increased. Well, that's an
interpretation that's been given to it
throughout history, and that's
evolved throughout history.
Before it was said that if M increased more
rapidly than Q, inflation occurred.
In the new texts we have today, it's
said that if M increases, P increases
immediately. Why? Because Q
varies very little, and because V, the
velocity of circulation, are also practically
constant at an instant in time. But
that's a bad interpretation, because
we have to look at this over the
course of a year, not when when
the time limit tends to zero.
We'll look at it later. When I look at it
over a year, in a year, what happens? One
has to increase the money
supply to the extent that Q increases,
and there we try to keep prices
constant.
When we have this over the year,
it means that if we go to time t equals
0, that is, in day to day, on the day of
today, so to speak, the emission will be
1/365th of what I'm going to do in
the year, that is, it'll be a very
small thing, and so, speaking in
small terms, a very small thing
won't modify this, but will modify
production. Production
daily is
growing or slowing, but
depending on how you handle
money. These equations were expressed by
Keynes, and Keynes, well, did more. He did,
he spoke of a fifth, which I maintain
isn't necessary to handle, because
about this, what it does is muddy the
discourse a bit. He spoke of another
proposition, that the marginal
efficiency of capital reaches the point where it
equals the interest rate. I
add with the deposit
interest rate, it's my addition. Keynes reached
here, up to the interest rate.
Keynes spoke a lot about the interest
rate, but never expressed it as deposit
interest rate of the financial
system plus the intermediation
interest rate of the financial system. That
he only spoke of the interest rate, in my
view, he fell short. It was necessary to
open the expression and analyze them one by
one. But he spoke of the interest rate.
I add this other equation for the
same context: that sales, in general,
global, in an economy, equal
P times Q, almost what we were talking about here. Not
exactly, but it's like, like like in
GDP. A social P, let's speak of a social
GDP, where sales will
equal costs, plus expenses, plus
interest, plus taxes, plus
profits. Or removing from those sales
all these expenses, we're left with the
social profits of the entire system. And
I'd add a following equation, which
is like a result of the management that
happens here, which is that inflation
depends on costs, on the money
supply, and particularly, within those
costs, on the deposit
interest rate. It's fundamental in the theoretical
context we're going to look at here, in this
context. Keynes said the following. Keynes
analyzed this as a
system, and said: gentlemen, look carefully,
all the variables are there. When I
speak of income, production,
consumption, I can break this down as
household consumption or government
consumption. I'm talking about all the
variables, the money supply,
supply and demand for products,
supply and demand for savings and
investment, supply and
demand in general. And Keynes made an
analysis. Keynes wanted to know what were
the independent variables of that
system. When he said: what were the
independent variables of the system,
he wanted to know how the
system could be managed. Where was the secret
to managing the system? And he discovered
that the independent variables of the
system were the money supply and the
interest rate. And we're going to handle
this discourse very well. Notice that
in current theory, we're told
that if the money supply increases,
inflation occurs. I'm going to contradict
that later. And it tells us that if
the interest rate increases,
we can control inflation.
I'm also going to contradict that
point, but I won't contradict it,
you'll realize yourselves
that it's
false. When Keynes said these two were
the independent variables of the system,
it means whoever manages these two
variables manages the entire economy,
invariably.
When we separated and gave to the
central banks so they manage
the money supply and interest rate, and
the government manages the the product, the
gross domestic product, and production, and
consumption, and regulates, then,
employment, we made, we committed a very
big sin, which was to divide the system. The
system is indivisible. The system is one
single thing, and everything works in perfect unity.
When we divided it, we told some
gentlemen: manage this. We gave
all the power of the economic system to
some people to manage. We gave it
to the central banks, because at
this moment the central banks, all
in the world, manage these two
variables, and we gave them
independence from the government. So,
it means that independence is
inclined, rather, toward management by
private interests. I want to tell you, with
this, that here we're seeing that we have
to rejoin
the money supply and the interest rate
so the government manages it, as the
social element it is and that represents
the community in general, and not
private interests. Well, in this
context, this is the development I
wanted to discuss right now.
We'll develop this a bit more later,
but in a visual way so everyone
can understand, and right now I'll
leave it at that point. We're going to
continue, then, with our second
part: economic policies. Notice
we're giving them separately, and
then we'll
interrelate them. So, the second
part tells us: economic policies. I'm
going to talk to you, in general, about eight
policies. I only chose these eight,
although the most important are three. No,
more, I chose these eight, because they're the ones that
define the macroeconomic system for me in
broad strokes.
There are many more policies, because
every country goes on developing
employment policies later, social
security policies, policies for
agricultural development, for all
fields. In all fields, in all
three sectors of the economy. But
with these eight, in
general, we define the general context of
a country. How a country should be managed.
So, we talk about the free
market, for example, and the free market
can, at a given
moment, define, we define as
policy that we don't have free market, or
that we do have free market, or a combined
range,
right. Tariffs, we can say no,
that we don't have them, or that we do. Interest
rates, similarly, we have a very large
range to choose a defined
policy. So, let's see, for example, what
the International Monetary
Fund tells us about free market. It
tells us we have to apply it 100%.
About tariffs, it tells us we have
to eliminate tariffs, and well, that
has its explanation, which to all of us seems
reasonable.
We should eliminate
tariffs so more free
trade is generated, which helps lower
prices, competition helps prices
drop, and and countries thus
benefit from being able to acquire
cheaper things. About interest
rates, they
tell us it's better if they're high so
that, so that countries attract
external capital, attract foreign
investment. It tells us that fiscal
deficit we should eliminate.
The IMF is International Monetary Fund. What
they sold us with globalization
are the policies that define
globalization for us. So, that fiscal
deficit we should eliminate. What does
that mean? That governments equal
their current income they have with
their expenses, that it doesn't go into debt. This, this,
we need to see if that's possible to do in
practice, in reality. They told us
it had to be done, but no, they never
gave us an analysis of whether that was
possible or not, and people believe it's
possible, but that's, that's the
challenge. They told us, then, that if we didn't
manage to maintain a fiscal deficit,
we'd have to go into debt.
So, these two are combined. The
debt, then, must be generated. If
this doesn't happen, there'll be
debt. Money issuance, that
is, the Central Bank making money
for the government, so the government
spends it, that these emissions
shouldn't be made, and they told us very clearly
that because that caused inflation. You
remember I told you already that that
inflation we still didn't have very clear
what caused it. They tell us that
inflation is caused by that money
emission, and that it shouldn't be done, and in fact,
it's prohibited in the entire world. Even in
the United States, we'll see how that
provision makes countries,
inevitably, reach a crisis.
But we'll see it
later. Taxes, they tell us: well, if
not to have to go into debt, then
we have to collect more taxes, and
taxes should be high. And then,
to be able to pay those deficits, it's better to
privatize the entire economy, privatize
public services, oil,
privatize absolutely all the the
the elements, companies the
government has.
Well. But, but notice well, this is a
combination of many possible,
undoubtedly. When they told us
globalization, that had to be proven
first that that's the best
way. They never proved anything to us. They
told us: do this, and the world went
headfirst to do that, and today we're
suffering consequences, and we don't
know why. We're going to try to see
what happens. But right now, what I
want to see with this table is that
we analyze other possibilities for
the same globalization, because, indeed,
the that combination of policies, well, there are
many possibilities. I want to
show you what
Keynes said. Keynes spoke of the free
market, yes, but with some
restrictions. That is, not so 100%, all the way.
He told us that tariffs,
you had to be a bit careful with
tariffs to protect the internal
market a bit. So, not very high,
but, but you did have to put certain
tariffs. About interest rates, in
Keynes, definitely, interest
rates should always be low. That
was very clear in his theoretical context.
About fiscal deficit, Keynes understood
that government was an essential engine
for
that, that, that engine to move the
economy. So, fiscal deficit, yes,
had to exist. He understood that the State's
mere income isn't sufficient,
but the State has to be an
engine in spending so the economy
is is activated. We'll see it
later, a bit clearer. The
debt, in Keynes, is very clear,
it has to happen. That is, Keynes doesn't speak of
free money emissions. He doesn't speak of
very restricted money emissions,
but debt has to occur.
That he always saw banking as very, very
important. He could never
break free from debt. Our
current civilization is the civilization
of debt. We're all used to
having to resort to debt. I'm
going to tell you it's not necessarily
true. About money issuance, Keynes:
it should happen,
indeed. Not much. Taxes, in
Keynes, shouldn't be so high. They should be just
regulated. And about privatizations, he's
not very much in agreement, Keynes. Keynes
understands that part of the
State's function is is to provide service in
those places where private
parties aren't, aren't, aren't very sociable to do
that kind of work. Well, as
you see, look, there's another possible
combination, and I want to show you that there
are still many more combinations, and
I'm going to show you one more. You'll
be shocked with
this. Globalization, for example, according to a
new model. Maybe I can
prove to you that this, that this other
possibility is much better than the two
previous ones. One in which free
market, we don't have free market. That is,
I accept free market. I think the
free market is the best of
systems to bring to
civilization all possible elements of
development. The, I want to
clarify a point. Free market is not the
market. Let's say, it's like the sun that
illuminates everyone, rich and poor
alike. The market does the, does the
same. The market doesn't look at morality. The
market, simply, functions. But that
market functions according to the
amount of money in the system.
If money is very little, then the the
market takes care of ejecting everything, and and
puts everything with the amount of money
there is. If there's lots of money, it allows
many people to enter. The market doesn't look, doesn't
look at people. The market,
simply, makes the
system function according to the amount of
money there is. So, what this leads
us to is what Keynes told us, that
what we have to control is the money
supply, money issuance, if
we want to control the system. No.
So, the market isn't good per se,
it's not bad per se. The market is something that
functions according to how you
feed it. Tariffs, I agree
on eliminating tariffs. Yes, very well.
We can eliminate tariffs. Interest
rates, definitely, I
agree they should be very low, really,
lower than Keynes's. I think it can
happen. But what's very clear about
interest rates is that the deposit
interest rate of the financial
system should be eliminated, should be zero,
and we'll see why. We'll see it
later. About fiscal deficit, I want to
say that government can spend
everything
needed. Consumption, as we saw before,
consumption of families and
government, government should fuel a
consumption such that it's sufficient
to also fuel the the market
and the capitalist
system can function. It's something like
saying the capitalist system has
to be composed of half socialist and
half capitalist. That socialist part,
let's call it that, is what feeds
resources to the system so
capitalists can work
permanently. Fiscal deficit must
exist, and it can be as high as
required, high enough for the
system to generate employment for
absolutely all people of working
age, for all people.
So, that, what does it mean? That
debt, or you'd believe that
debt should be very large. No,
look, debt can be zero,
as long as we make money
issuance, then, from the Central Bank
directly to governments, without
need for loan or anything. The
money resource is unlimited. The problem is
how we can use it. Later
we'll explain all this. How, already in visual
form, by breaking down the the systems and
looking at how the economic system works,
then we'll see that
point more clearly. Right now, I'm just
announcing it. Those money emissions
can be made
freely, and zero debt. Taxes,
in this case, can be low,
quite low, just to make an
equitable redistribution of money
throughout the entire population. The
privatizations can be done, but
as long as there's competition in the
market, there's competition in supply. It's
more important that there's competition in
supply when dealing with, for example,
public
services. So, look, we have three
possibilities. Not to mention there are more
possible combinations. It's that
when we talk about economic
policies of
globalization, it means we can
combine, make many
combinations. The question would be: which of all the
policies is the best? And
it's very important to be able to solve that
question. Will the International Monetary
Fund's be the best? We don't know.
That had to be proven. It had to
set the context and develop it, and
we still don't
know. The context we're going to propose
will allow us to define what's the
best policy of
all. This problem, what is the best
combination of these policies? So,
let's make, let's make a very
important simulation to to be able to see the
general economic system, to separate
the parts of that system, see how
each each part works and how it works
as a whole. We're going to
arrive at this great economic system where
we're going to relate everything. Don't
be scared. Everything, when explained bit by
bit, comes out simpler. This
economic system we're going to integrate,
we're going to talk about a a country, a country
that has a Central Bank, a country
that develops a money supply, and money
supply that sometimes increases and sometimes
decreases. A country that has
exports and imports. A country
that receives credit, receives foreign
investment, sells assets, and receives income.
A country that manages international
reserves through an exchange
rate.
A country that has a government that acts
and has income and budget
expenditures. A country where all
economic activity develops in
its three basic activities:
agriculture, the the agro sector, the primary sector,
the secondary sector of industry, and the
tertiary sector of services,
including banking. A country where
government does a type of works, where
government also intervenes in the in the
economy. A country where banking is
receiving some some resources that
we call deposits, where it
interrelates with interest rates,
and lends to industry. Industry
and private individuals go into debt through
their costs and commercial activity,
where investment is generated and
the entire system interrelates. So,
to be able to see that whole, we're going to
develop it bit by bit. So, we're going to
develop this first part first
which is the one we
have
here. We have a country, any,
any, any country could be
the United States, could be Colombia, could
be China, could be Russia, could be
whichever you want.
All countries function more or less
the same way. We have a Central
Bank in those countries. We have a
government that's executing
income and budget
income. We have a country that's
receiving money from many
sources. We'll see them. Money that
sometimes increases, sometimes decreases.
What's needed for the country to always
be working perfectly well? That
money is always
increasing. It must be permanently
increasing, because the country is
permanently
growing. For you to get
an idea of how serious it is not to have
money, then suddenly take
money from the system. Imagine it. This
you have to grasp in your imagination.
Take money from the system and think
what happens. If we take money from the
system, the system runs out
of money. Then, ah, you'll immediately
say: no, well then we have to
barter. No, barter worked
when there were very few people, but
today, with this huge number of people, do you think
barter will work? Forget it. The
economy will stagnate, and the population
could starve to death if there's no
money in the system.
No money, all
trade stops, absolutely everything.
Imagine it well. Then
you'll understand how important
money supply control is in the
system. If the system oscillates, we'll
have, then, crises. If at a given
moment we have a good money supply, that's
growing, and money is cheap,
we'll have expansion. But if
suddenly we stop it and raise the
interest rate, and start taking money
from the system, we'll have contraction.
When the Central Bank says: we have to
raise the interest rate, and we have to
reduce public spending, then it's
saying to take money from the
system, and the system starts to
contract, and the crisis starts to be seen.
So, what's the deal with
money? How does money emerge into the
economy and how does money leave the
economy? We have to analyze that that
aspect. So, let's go step by step. When
people found gold, gold
prospectors found gold, and
came and sold it to the government, to the
Central Bank, and the Central Bank
bought that gold, and pesos emerged into the
economy. Pesos emerged into the economy
when we find gold. Pesos emerge into the
economy if they sell it directly
to the Central Bank. The Central Bank issues
money, and pesos emerge into the economy.
Very important,
right? When we did that, we're
stuck with, then, the
backing for money was gold. I want to
tell you right away: money doesn't need
backing for
anything. That was a historical stage, but
that was abandoned long ago. The
people, perhaps, still think
backing is needed, but it's not true. It's
not needed. That emerged in that era, and
we're stuck with that gum there,
but we have to erase that, if
we want to keep evolu-
ting. Money doesn't need backing of
any kind. Well, another way money emerges
into the economy: when we make
exports.
Our agents here make an
export, for example, we export coffee,
and from outside they pay us in dollars.
Dollars that, when they enter here, stay
in a box called reserves, which
the Central Bank manages, and it issues pesos
to
to whoever made the export, and pesos
emerge for the domestic
economy. Those pesos increase when
there are exports. But when there are
imports, then the agent who
made the import needs to pay in
dollars. So, they have to take pesos
from here, from circulation, come here and
buy
dollars, and the pesos, notice, that come and
return to the Central Bank, and
disappear from from
circulation. And then, this agent,
with dollars, pays that
import. Well, exports increase
money, imports decrease
money.
When credit comes from
abroad, a company here requests a
loan, a company could be the same
government requesting a loan, could
be a private company requesting a
loan.
When that happens, then
credit comes, the bank's reserves
increase, and the bank issues pesos. Pesos
emerge into the
economy. When a foreign agent
comes to make an investment, when an
oil company comes to invest, it brings
dollars, and pesos are issued, and
reserves increase.
Well, that's how pesos emerge into the
economy. What happens later when the
credit has to be repaid? Then, people, the
people here have to take pesos from here,
and pay. They bring pesos, buy dollars, and pay
in dollars. What happened to the pesos? They
came to the Central Bank, pesos left
the economy's circulation. The
pesos, when they enter the Central Bank,
disappear from the economy's
circulation, and we need the
pesos to be here circulating. So, there
we see that sometimes it increases, and sometimes
it decreases. When investment also
starts reverting profits, then
the reverse process: pesos come to
the Central Bank, and are paid in dollars.
When we sell, what happens when we sell
an asset or a company? When we sold,
uh, the energy company, the energy
company was sold, dollars entered,
but then, they start taking
out
profits. So, what, what happens?
We take pesos from here, buy dollars,
and are paid in dollars. So, pesos start
leaving. Very well. Here we could
ask ourselves a question: if no more
elements existed, but only these,
imports, exports, which is what
we call the the the
the trade balance, or the balance of
payments, when we combine both with
with internal gold resources, we can
ask ourselves: if no more elements exist,
what could be happening here with
pesos? With the entry and exit of
pesos. So, what will be greater? The
exports or the imports?
These two, I want to tell you, in general,
tend to balance. They tend to be
equal. If nothing else existed, these
two should be equal, and then the
dollar price, according to the
amount of reserves there are, the price
can rise or fall, and it rises and falls in such a
way that it balances these
two. Let's say, a tie there. But this can
become unbalanced at some given
moment. We'll see later.
What happens with credit? What will be greater,
income or outflow? So, now
putting this to work over time,
a 10-year loan, so, at
the beginning, no, the loan came in, very well,
good money came in, but later you have to
you have to pay it back in the term of 10 years.
What will be better, the greater, income or
outflow of money? So, you, of course,
you have to pay not only the loan, the
loan amount,
the loan, but also the interest.
So, will the outflows
of money be greater, right? When long-term
investment comes, what will be greater,
entry or
exit? Exit. When there's asset
sales, what will be greater, entry or
exit? So, everyone will agree that
money outflow, so, if no
more elements exist, you'll
realize why a crisis arrives, because
outflows will be greater. Money
outflows. You'll say: but,
but, but, isn't that what's happening
right now.
Right now all that is happening, but
many dollars are arriving. Yes, but
we're still going into debt,
into debt, into debt, and then those
greater debts make reserves
increase. You, have you noticed
we have very high reserves,
almost in the order of 25,000 million
of of of
dollars, a
huge amount. And that makes the dollar
low. We're still going into debt, in
the debt process.
So, when all that has to be paid,
the whole mess will unravel, and the
crisis will be terrible. In fact, we
already have a crisis right now. What happens,
then, if there are no more elements but
those? So, realize, that first we
go into debt. When we go into debt,
reserves increase. Notice that the
dollar price is very special. When
there are many dollars, its price drops. When
the price drops, then
imports, since they get
cheaper, will increase. We unbalance
the trade balance, right? So, when
we unbalance that balance,
then, internally, very
cheap products enter, and our industry has
difficulty. It's going to, it's going to start closing,
it's going to start failing. It can't handle
that competition. How did
this become unbalanced? With credit, with many dollars.
Many dollars, low price, and then
this trade balance became unbalanced. In
fact, since we started, more or less
in '91, that before imports and
exports oscillated, they stopped
oscillating, and imports are always
greater, since, since back then,
since '91, when that
globalization began in Colombia, when that
globalization of not issuing money
began in Colombia. So, notice how we can also
feed this system. The Central Bank
makes a money issuance, and gives it to the
government so the government includes it
within its income, and within its
expenses. Government expenses are
operating
expenses, investment expenses, and
debt
service. Government income is
current income and capital
resources. Well, that money being made
can come as a capital resource.
Normally, that capital resource is what
enters as a debt, a debt from the
Central Bank, or a debt from other
banks. The government goes into debt with other
banks. So, it's a capital resource.
This capital resource can be a
very special thing, because it wouldn't have to
be
a loan, but a resource from
itself, because the Central Bank and
government are the same, and money is
money that's socially needed. So,
then, money can enter
government not as a loan, but as the
the part, the contribution needed for
that year. Notice that makes
debt disappear. So, yes, a
country can function without debt, with this
issuance resource, to balance those
money inflows and outflows, to
balance so money grows
permanently.
In what amounts? In the amounts
needed for employment to be generated
for the entire population, not until
prices overflow. No, what's needed. The
thing is that this resource is unlimited.
The fundamental thing is the universe is
unlimited. The universe can give us
absolutely everything we want, and
here, money is also unlimited.
We've always fought that we don't
have money, that money is
held by the Americans and Europeans. They
do it the same way. They do it from
here, so, and they do it with, that's why I
was saying this can be any country
in in the world. Well, that money would enter, and
notice, would enter balancing a
need. Would it produce
inflation
necessarily? We're giving the money
needed for all
production to keep growing permanently.
So, no, it's not necessarily
inflationary. In fact, it's not
inflationary. What's more, once there's
good money circulating in the system,
a moment came when
producers have so much
competition arise, that prices have to
fall, and would tend to fall, if at the beginning
there is inflation. Well, what's
important is that money enters for
government, and government, as it would
deposit it in a bank, then a
multiplier factor enters on the banking
side, which would make, when government
is going to buy from a
private party, that private party can
find resources also to
go into debt with banking, and be able to respond,
and production can emerge, in balance, with
demand. So, no, no,
there's no reason for that inflation to be generated. Let's make
a simulation, a very
special simulation. Let's make a bridge, a
bridge with issuance, and let's make a bridge
with debt, and we're going to see how
things work. Let's first make the bridge
with debt, sorry, with issuance.
So, what happens? Government, the Central
Bank makes a money issuance, delivers it
to government, which puts it within
its income, and through spending,
as investment spending, makes the bridge.
So, what happened? It stayed, the money
supply increased, money stayed
circulating among everyone, among the entire
country, the bridge was made, and the money stayed
circulating. It won't return, because it
doesn't have to return. It stayed circulating
there, and so it remains permanently
functioning. Let's now make that same
bridge with with debt. So, what's the
system to do that? Credit comes
from abroad, credit that leaves
reserves, and they're monetized. So, the
Central Bank issues money, too,
but then
a part stayed here, in
reserves. Money was issued, the bridge
was made, the same way, but we're left
owing a bridge and some
interest. I don't know if you can realize
how unfair it is to be left owing
a bridge with interest, when this
way we made the bridge, and money was left
circulating, and we're not left owing
anyone. We made the bridge, and we're left
owing
everything. This, both the bridge and the
interest. That is, that these
developing countries that resorted to
credit, end up paying the pensioners
of the countries that made the loan.
That, that's what happens with
going into debt with international banking.
That's debt. Debt, and it enslaves,
enslaves nations. What I'm
talking about here is there's no need to
be enslaved. All countries
can do this mechanism, and all
countries
can eliminate debt, stop being a
debt country, a country enslaved by
debt. It means all countries
have the capacity to win their own
freedom, and have the
necessary resources to
have what's needed for their subsistence
and spend their life on this, on this
planet. But the story of
of the bridge with debt doesn't end there, because
it turns out those reserves, means
imports increased. You
remember, greater amount of reserves,
lower foreign prices, and then
these people take their income to
buy cheaper abroad, and they
go back and recover the
money. Their dollars go back and they
recover them, and we do destroy
our own industries, in favor of
of foreigners. So, the
panorama of of debt is complete. The country that
goes into debt with another, immediately passed
to being enslaved, buying all
products, unbalancing its own
trade
balance, and entering a very
complicated situation. What happens when
issuance isn't made? When we deny issuance,
like we did right now, that
we said in the Constitution of '91, and in
general, in all countries, at their
moment, they prohibited Central Bank
credits to government. Central Bank
credit to government cannot be made. These
issuances we're talking about cannot be made. So,
what happens? Well, we already saw it, we already know
that, then, the country runs out
of money. How does
the president of that country act then? What
does he have to do? Since, since he knows he doesn't
have money, and needs money,
forcibly, then, he has to resort to
a
loan. A loan to increase this
money supply, right? The loan comes,
the money supply increases, and vi, then,
and it has to be paid later, with
interest. When the moment comes to
pay the debt,
would be left with that hole, the money
supply would decrease. So, to be able to pay
that, he has to get credit
exactly
equal, plus a larger
credit, plus interest, that later, to
be able to pay this, then, he has to
get credit to be able to pay. That
is, he ends up always renegotiating
debt. That is, he ends up always giving away
the
interest, permanently renegotiating
debt. That is, debt that
will permanently keep increasing. That's
why, all countries that started the
globalization tale and not issuing,
the first thing that's grown on them
impressively is debt, and
debt has tied them, then, to the
will of of banks, and what
bankers
define. Because, besides, we
made central banks independent, and
put bankers there, who only
defend the interests of banking, of
banking, of private banking. So,
countries, what did they end up in? In an
increase of debt. And that's something
explosive, for this reason. When we don't
issue, you can say it's
a matter of time. The catastrophe will
come. It's inevitable, and we're
seeing it, because the United States is also
complying with
this. Despite that at this moment, in
the United States they're processing a
credit of 700,000 million
dollars. If they don't keep doing it
permanently, then they'll have
this situation. Sooner or later, they give
it a respite, but later they'll
have the same situation again. Same as all
Europe, same as everything, the whole world.
So, that's what happens when we don't
issue. When we don't issue,
we're left enslaved. To be able to pay this,
imagine what we'd have to do.
An army of ours go and make them
the same bridge, there in the United States, on
our behalf, and make the bridge, and bring
on our behalf our people, and
be able to settle the situation? When, look,
with money issuance alone, we can
make our bridge, and our economy
remains
sound. This tells us that no
country should have debt. No country
has a reason to enslave another, and all
could
live well enough from their own
work. No country has a reason to go
exploit
another. When we talk about exploitation
of one country by another, it's because we think
that resources are limited, and that this
we can't do. Well, and there's another
element we have more, more ahead.
Well, let's see, let's go to the second part
of of the
problem. How does this interest rate thing
work? We have a Central
Bank,
any bank, a bank that collects
resources from the public, and in exchange for those
public resources, pays an interest
rate we call deposit
interest. It pays to the, we've called
this term very badly, to the savers.
No, these aren't savers. Savings is
a very different concept in economics. We
already saw before. It's not the money that, that
banks pay. That's deposit
interest.
Banks take is those
resources they collected from the public, and
lend them to companies. At what rate do
they lend them? Well, at an interest rate
that includes this deposit rate, obviously,
they repeat it, plus an intermediation
rate. So, these rates are
being transmitted from bank to
company. And, what does the company,
then, do with those expenses it has
there? It's paying interest. Where
is it charging this? Well, all that it's
going to send to the product
price, and then the product
price returns it to the the general
public, it includes again what it
is
being paid in those interest payments. That is,
it's generating inflation. That de-, that
deposit rate, is generating
inflation. Notice that inflation, I'm
telling you here, isn't produced by
money issuance. It's produced by that interest
rate.
Well, the company returns it, and charges.
But, what does the interest rate do? The interest
rate is as if it decreased the
money supply. So, it'll generate a
crisis. It'll generate a crisis, it's going
to generate that the, the
business owners have that as competition,
that deposit interest rate, and can't
generate all the sales they
require. There are many expenses that that go
to this point. So, the
companies won't employ all the
people they could employ, if that
rate
didn't exist. In fact, it cut the money supply.
So, that makes there be fewer
companies. So, that deposit interest
rate not only is
recessionary, but, well, it's going to
necessarily generate a residual margin of
unemployment that can't, that can't. There's a
very large margin that will never
be employed. Well, that's the phenomenon of
the deposit interest rate. What
to do?
Eliminate it.
Ah, but then, who's going to
put their money in the bank if they're not paid
anything? Everyone will keep taking
their money to the bank, because no one's going to
walk around with 50 million pesos in their
pocket, putting themselves here, for it to be
stolen. No, people will keep taking
their money to the bank. What's going to happen is
that, if people have a lot of money in the
bank, they'll is move it. They'll set up an
industry, they'll buy land, and they're going to
make a building to rent
apartments, and they'll earn their
wages
by working, their salary by working, and not
like a drone, waiting for the bank
to pay them interest. I want to say that
those who, generally, have money, have been
industrialists, people who know how to work. They
don't care about this rate.
They'd earn more outside. What
happens is that this rate competes with
industry, whereas industry
has to
employ many people, with deal with
suppliers, with employees, with machinery,
with everything, to earn a profit. The
bank,
simply, offers that same
profit, without doing absolutely anything.
So, there's a limit, that if you
have, for example, 100 million pesos,
and doing all this, you'll get a
profit of 8%, well, you put the money
in the bank, because the bank gives 8%.
So, you stopped making an industry,
because this put a lower limit on
the
industries. That deposit interest is
competing, making industries
not develop as far as they should
go, generating that, that unemployment.
Well, if the scheme is clear, very simple,
besides.
We can see that, when the Central Bank
and all analysts tell us we have to
raise the interest rate to
control inflation, it's false. The
inflation will be generated by that interest
rate. Why did we come to believe that that
interest would reduce inflation?
Because theory tells us that, when that
interest rate is raised, the money
supply is reduced, company
sales are reduced, and when
demand drops, then, prices will drop.
But no, it's not true. Prices won't
drop, because production also drops,
and they're left, both are reduced,
supply and demand, and prices
continue. Why? Those interest
payments that are there go
to the product price. So, there's no
such thing. The government tells
us, analysts, today today,
tell us three elements: that we have to
raise the interest rate, that we have to
reduce public spending, and that
issuances
can't be made. So, now, let's put all
the discourse together. Let's put all the
discourse back together, and then, how does that
first part combine with the interest
part? We already know, then, what happens
when we raise the interest rate,
as all analysts tell us.
We also already know what happens when
we reduce the the public spending. When
we reduce public spending, it
means we don't make issuances. So,
we're going to run out of money.
So, the economy will contract. It
contracts when we reduce public
spending. The economy contracts. As
all analysts tell us, what
we have to do to solve the
crisis: raise the interest rate and
reduce public spending. Well, there we
realize what they're
asking us is to go into a
crisis. That is, what all
analysts are telling us right now is wrong, that
the remedy is to raise the rate and
reduce public spending. Well, let's put,
then, the discourse together. So, how can
society work for us? Well, we already
know, then, that if we make money
issuance, we don't have to go into debt.
By not having to go into debt,
then, imports and
exports will balance. At
the beginning, at the beginning, there'll be the
adjustment. And it's that returning
starts, well, what we're already owing, which
should, rather, be cancelled, because that
was theft. But, well, let's say we
can make the adjustment, returning to
to everyone what we once
negotiated. Anyway, we already know
how we can get out of the problem.
The
reserves, the exchange rate, has a
high equilibrium point, or low.
We hope to reach
equilibrium. When the exchange
rate is low, imports grow. When
we make issuances, we don't go further into debt.
So, those reserves will start being
paid, will start being paid, and they'll
start being depleted, and the
dollar price will start rising. So, it'll
be at a high level. At that
high level of dollar price, the
imports will decrease, and
exports will increase.
And then, that will happen
while the the system
balances again. What we have to reach, in
all countries, is that we all must
be in balance, both internally and
externally. Then, at that moment,
we'll have maximum justice, all
countries with maximum development,
because they have their own resources,
they have their labor force, and they have their
work to do. It's not fair to
have roads in very bad condition, and and
people unemployed, for lack of money.
Well, then, how does the part with
government work? Notice that government
has its income and its
expenses: current income and the capital
resource part, which are
loans, they have to balance those
expenses. Well.
When we make the issuance to
finance that part there,
that, that part of the deficit, that issuance
comes to make different types of
works, to to complement, in addition to
the money already circulating, in
addition to current income, there's some
additional income that's going to increase
the economy's money, and that allows
everyone to keep growing.
So, we're going to make roads, schools,
hospitals, transportation, aqueduct,
sewerage, and we can do
reforestation and
decontamination, because what's
needed is people's work. The
money,
look, can do everything you want.
So, this changes the discourse for us. That
additional income the
economy receives, no, it's not only for
government, but these people who
receive that of income, will also buy
from the other companies that are
there, from schools, from hospitals, from
food, from clothing. The
entire economy will move. We're, we're going to have
a multiplier factor. At the beginning, it's
possible we'll have demand-pull
inflation, but over time, the
companies, whose
interest rate has been lowered, then, will be able to
produce more. In fact, they'll produce more,
because they'll receive more sales. The
companies' sales will increase
permanently. Every year they'll
increase. There's no reason for there to be crises.
Crises are fomented, they're
contrived. Right now, when
we do that, permanently, we're not going to
have crises anymore. So, companies
will, will have more profits, and they'll
also increase their their
investment: more employment, more supply, less
inflation, more employment, more income, and
then, the economy will keep turning
permanently
in a stable growth
permanently, as the human
being deserves, I'd
say. We've already gone through many stages of
much suffering, much hunger, of
many problems and economic hardships, and
man, it's time for him to learn from
his experience, and know that he can also
live happily in this, in this world. Here
is the solution to the economic problem.
Happiness, that will be an internal
problem for for each person, of religion,
perhaps, of people harmonizing with their
own religion. But in the economic
part, resources can be harmonized
so humanity lives
perfectly well, without slaves, without, without
wars. There's no reason for it
to happen. So, let's see what
the policies told us. Which of all the
policies was the best? The Monetary
Fund's, that told us free market,
that very high interest rates, that
fiscal deficit, no? Fiscal deficit, yes.
When they tell us fiscal deficit, no, they
make us put the economy into a crisis.
When they tell us
debt, well, I just
showed you how all civilization can
leave the debt problem, can
leave debt, and can live
happily, with all the resources it
desires. Money issuance, that the
Monetary Fund told us shouldn't be done, and
we see that yes, it should be
done. They give us Monetary
Fund
International policies. We
saw it: reduce money, raise the
interest rate, is taking us to a
crisis, inevitably.
Let's discard, then, the economic
globalization policies the
International Monetary Fund sold us.
We've been able to prove that, indeed,
they're false, they're false, they're wrong.
Let's see this other aspect of the economic
system in general, and basically, all
countries, let's say, that
have the primary sector, the secondary
sector, and, and the tertiary sector, in, in which
all companies are managed for
mining, agriculture, livestock,
etcetera, the secondary sector, industries and
construction, the tertiary sector,
banks, services, well, funds,
etcetera. Governments, generally,
have their executive, legislative, and
judicial branch, and their control bodies, and
have financial entities for
supporting the different economic
sectors, and have their central bank,
which is the base, which is what produces
money, and we have here, on this side, the
context of economic theory, which tells
us what we saw at the
beginning: income and production, the
quantitative equation of money, the
velocity of circulation, and the money
supply, the interest rate, and
controlling inflation.
Well, we already know that controlling
inflation, then, isn't going to be
raising the interest rate, but
eliminating the deposit rate, and
letting the intermediation rate, the
free market one, depending on the
competition the different
banks make. What's important is this: that
we
separated, and in general, in all
countries, the management of the real
variables of the economy was separated.
It was given to the executive to
control them, and the monetary variables were
given to the central bank to
control them. And also, we handed over the
central bank to the independence
of of private parties, that don't listen
to the executive. Well, why? Why was
that need made? So that the central
bank introduces money to
through banks. So, the
process comes: the central bank makes
the money, delivers it to the banks, and
the banks lend it to
government. When we could make the money
directly, give it to government, without
need for so much intermediation or so much interest
rate.
We've already seen how money works.
So, why did central banks
ask for independence? Well of course,
you can't imagine the business that
moves when we do this. No, the
central banks, with control of the
money supply and interest rate, and
indebting government, and when they indebt
government, the go, the executive, to
be able to pay, well indebts everyone,
with
taxes. That's the procedure that
we must reject, and that we must change
for the new era of human
liberation. We have to reject that process
that enslaves, and do our own,
directly. The central bank,
really, should be a wing of
government, where government makes the
money the economy needs,
directly, without credit, without interest, and
distributes it to the economy, puts it into
circulation through the works of the
executive, of infrastructure
works, or through its
different control bodies, that can
help the different companies.
And banking, how does it benefit from all
this? In that government, when it receives
money, government will use
banking, anyway. It'll put the
money in banking, and banking will be able to
distribute and lend to private parties,
but not indebting government or the
country directly. So, what happened with
our system when we separated it?
We committed a very big sin, because the
system is one. The system must be unique,
and all countries can do this
situation: reunite this, recover
their central banks,
and eliminate debt.
Well, I'd like to make an introduction of
what would be,
then, the unique money on planet
Earth, under the same
principle. Let's say, then, that this isn't
a country, but that it's planet Earth,
where we have an
executive, the different sectors of the
economy, and some control ones. Well it
means that the bank, no longer central,
but at world level, we should
have a single bank. But a single bank
that wouldn't belong to any particular
country, nor to any particular
entity. It would belong to all
countries. Let's say all countries
could meet and make a single bank, and
that single bank would have to make an
annual distribution of money, change
in all countries the money for that
single currency. That single bank would have to
give money each year to the new, to the
countries, not as
debt, but as: this is the equity that
corresponds to you to spend
this year, to increase your production in
this year. And all countries could go
tied to a, to a single inter-
national currency, but with that equitable factor
of giving each one their
corresponding monetary unit each
year, so they keep growing. And thus
we could establish a new economic
system
worldwide. How far could this be?
Well, it depends on on how quickly
each country organizes, first,
individually,
so people level out, level out
in the, in the
socioeconomic, we all have a
balanced level of of life, and then, yes,
we could proceed to make the unique
integrated system
international. And in that way, perhaps,
legislation could be unified,
being equitable for for everyone. We've
finished the talk. It's Economic
Heresy, Protocols Toward a New
Economic System. It depends on you
to allow them not to keep stealing, not to
keep exploiting, not to
keep on. Well, it depends on you to win
the new planet Earth, with the
abundance we deserve, with the
happiness we deserve. This is a
new scientific and systemic method for
economic theory. This is the first
chapter of the book "Protocols Toward a
New Economic System". You were
addressed by Mauricio Rivadeneira Mora. It was a
pleasure.
[Music]